H. O. Hanson, Photograph Collection 1952-1957 Mss.B.H198
American Philosophical Society
H. O. Hanson Photograph Collection
1952-1957
Mss.B.H198
American Philosophical Society
0.1 Linear feet 34 images
The Santa Fe Fiesta and the Inter-Tribal Indian Ceremonial are two of the major cultural events held annually in New Mexico, both involving substantial participation by the Indian population of the state and region. The older of these, the Fiesta, originated in 1712 when the Spanish governor, the Marqués of Pañuela, set aside a day in September to commemorate the reconquest of the province by Don Diego de Vargas. Since 1919, the festival has been held annually and has increasingly become a celebration of traditional New Mexican culture and the varied ethnicities of its population. The Inter-Tribal Indian Ceremonial of Gallup, New Mexico, was organized by local businessmen and Indian traders in 1922 for "the encouragement of Indian arts and crafts and the education of whites to the beauties of Indian life" and for the "perpetuation of the dances, traditions and customs of Indian life." The H. O. Hanson Photograph Collection contains 34 large format (8x10") black and white prints, including sixteen images of the Inter-Tribal Ceremonial at Gallup, 1953 and 1954, four images of the Jemez Pueblo, and nine images of the Santa Fe Fiesta, 1952 and 1953. Hanson has not been further identified, but he may have worked for the Bureau of Indian Affairs.
Hanson, H. O.
Box 1
Related Archival Materials note
The Fray Angélico Chávez History Library at the Palace of the Governors, Santa Fe, houses a Santa Fe Fiesta Colletion (AC 201).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired from Almagre Books, March 2004 (accn. no. M2004-9).
Scope and Contents note
The H. O. Hanson Photograph Collection contains 34 large format (8x10") black and white prints, including sixteen images of the Inter-Tribal Ceremonial at Gallup, 1953 and 1954, nine images of the Santa Fe Fiesta, 1952 and 1953, and four images of the Jemez Pueblo. Hanson has not been further identified, but he may have worked for the Bureau of Indian Affairs. The photographs are somewhat unusual: mostly candid shots of the events, focused as much on the crowd as on the performers.
The title of each photograph is written on the verso, and most are signed and dated by the photographer. The images were originally affixed onto acidic mounts with staples (not affecting the photograph area), with the title transcribed beneath, however all of the images have now been removed and rehoused in polypropylene sleeves. In the few instances in which the transcribed title differed from that written on the image, both have been recorded, with the "alternate version" referring to the title on the mount.
Links to the digital versions of the photographs are included in the inventory. You may also view a gallery of all images here.
Biographical/Historical note
The Santa Fe Fiesta and the Inter-Tribal Indian Ceremonial are two of the major cultural events held annually in New Mexico, both involving substantial participation by the Indian population of the state and region. The older of these, the Fiesta, originated in 1712 when the Spanish governor, Joseph Chacón Medina Salazar y Villaseñor, the Marqués of Pañuela, set aside a day in September to commemorate the reconquest of the province by Don Diego de Vargas. Since 1919, the festival has been held annually and has increasingly become a celebration of traditional New Mexican culture and the varied ethnicities of its population.
The Inter-Tribal Indian Ceremonial of Gallup, New Mexico, was organized by local businessmen and Indian traders in 1922 for "the encouragement of Indian arts and crafts and the education of whites to the beauties of Indian life" and for the "perpetuation of the dances, traditions and customs of Indian life." The Ceremonial includes public performances of dances and songs, athletic contests, and an all-Indian rodeo, as well as opportunities to buy and sell arts and handicrafts. The Ceremonial draws participants from a number of tribes and nations, including the local Acoma, Hopi, Laguna, Navajo, and Zuni tribes. In 1939, the Inter-Tribal Indian Ceremonial was given official recognition by the state.
Gelatin silver prints; Indians of North America--Dance; Indians of North America--New Mexico; Indians of North America--Photographs; Inter-tribal Ceremonial (Gallup, N.M.)--Photographs; Jemez Indians--Photographs; Navajo Indians--Photographs; Photographs; Pueblo Indians--Photographs; Santa Fe (N.M.) Fiesta--Photographs; Santa Fe (N.M.)--Photographs; Southwest Indians; Zuni Indians
- H. O. Hanson, Photograph Collection, 1952-1957; 0.1 linear feet (Box 1)
  - Fiesta, Santa Fe, N. Mex. Governor's Palace, 1952 Oct. 31; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    View of rug and craft sales at Governor's Palace
  - Fiesta, Santa Fe, N. Mex. Indians selling on porch of Governor's Palace, 1952 Oct. 31; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Navajo craft sellers on porch of Palace
  - Indian Camp, Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1953 Oct. 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    View of tents and automobiles
  - Indian Camp, Indian Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1953 Oct. 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    View of tents
  - Indian Camp, Indian Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1953 Oct. 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Alt. title: "Indian Camp (Peter Pahona posing)"
  - Navajo couple watching parade, Indian Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1953 Oct. 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
  - Navajo mother, Indian Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1953 Oct. 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Woman holding infant with young girl.
  - Navajo transportation, Indian Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1953 Oct. 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    View of two girls sitting on sheepskins driving horse-drawn wagon
  - Navajos, Indian Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1953 Oct. 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Alt. title: "Navajo girls, Ceremonial"
  - Navajos watching parade, Indian Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1953 Oct. 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
  - Pueblo, Indian Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1953 Oct. 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    View of two elderly men riding donkeys
  - Pueblo Indian, Indian Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1953 Oct. 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Portrait of man wearing necklace and head scarf
  - Bottoms up, Santa Fe Fiesta, 1953 Aug. 29; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    View of young boy sitting on blankets, drinking Coke
  - Chico, Santa Fe Fiesta, 1953 Aug. 29; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    View of young boy dressed in Mexican outfit; Navajo man with rug in background
  - Mariachis on parade, Santa Fe Fiesta, 1953 Aug. 29; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Alt title: "Mariachis (troubadors)"
  - Parade, Santa Fe Fiesta, 1953 Aug. 29; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    View of Priests leading parade
  - Siesta, Santa Fe Fiesta, 1953 Aug. 29; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Alt title: "Fiesta siesta." Young girl asleep on mother's lap.
  - Sisters on parade, Santa Fe Fiesta, 1953 Aug. 29; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    View of nuns in parade
  - Talking it over, Pueblo Indians, Santa Fe Fiesta, 1953 Aug. 29; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
  - Pecos Pueblo, near Pecos, N. Mex. Abandoned 1828, 1953 Aug. 30; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    View of wooden cross and ruins of church (see Pecos Mission photos, Nov. 6, 1955)
  - Indian Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1954 Aug. 13; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    View of Zuni dancers on parade
  - Indian Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1954 Aug. 13; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Alt. title: "Zuni pottery and Zuni women, Gallup Indian Ceremonial"
  - Navaho, Gallup, N. Mex., 1954 Aug. 13; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Portrait of elderly Navajo man
  - Saving the Navahos, Tract peddlers, Gallup, N. Mex., 1954 Aug. 13; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Alt. title: "Giving religious tracts to the drunks, Gallup Indian Ceremonial"
  - Watching parade, Indian Ceremonial, Gallup, N. Mex., 1954 Aug. 13; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Alt. title: "Navahos watching the parade, Gallup Indian Ceremonial"
  - Watching rodeo, Ind. Cer., Gallup, N. Mex., 1954 Aug. 13; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Alt. title: "Rodeo fans"
  - Buffalo dancers, Jemez Pueblo, N. Mex., 1955 May 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
  - Eagle dancers, Jemez Pueblo, N. Mex., 1955 May 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
  - Indian boys, Jemez Pueblo, N. Mex., 1955 May 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
  - War dances, Jemez Pueblo, N. Mex., 1955 May 15; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
  - Pecos Mission ruins, 1955 Nov. 6; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    View of wooden cross and ruins. (See Pecos Mission photo Aug. 30, 1953)
  - Pecos Mission ruins, N. Mex., 1955 Nov. 6; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    View of wooden cross and ruins. (See Pecos Mission photo Aug. 30, 1953).
  - Easter morn, Santa Fe, N. Mex., 1957 Apr. 21; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Street scene downtown at movie theatre
  - Easter morn, Santa Fe, N. Mex., 1957 Apr. 21; 1 silverprint; Hanson, H. O. (Box 1)
    Street scene at corner of park